Guide to the Merritt family papers, 1841-1893.
Merritt family papers
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Merritt family papers, 1841-1893.
39J
94 letters (approximately 0.6 cubic feet).
Correspondence
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Letters and ledgers from various members of the Merritt family.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Letters from various members of the Merritt family, describing life along the Saint Lawrence River and in Saint Lawrence County and their pioneering travel west to Iowa, Wisconsin, Kansas, and Nebraska; much local color. Also several financial ledgers, account and day books, and some various publications.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Merritt family.; Merritt family.
Places:
Saint Lawrence River.; Saint Lawrence County (N.Y.); Middle West -- Description and travel.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Family Letters
  - Recipient: Darwin H. Merritt, September 18, 1841 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Address: East Pierrepont, St. Lawrence County, NY
    Sender: E. A. Merritt
    Letter #1
  - Recipient: Parker D. Merritt, November 5, 1841 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Address: West Stockholm, St. Lawrence County, NY
    Sender: H. H. Merritt
    Letter #2
  - Recipient: Noadiah Merritt, January 31, 1844 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Address: Pierrepont, St. Lawrence County, NY
    Sender: Emily, Ellen, Parker N. Merritt
    Letter #3
  - Recipient: Noadiah Merritt, November 14, 1845 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Letter #4
  - Recipient: Edwin A. Merritt, November 15, 1845 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Address: Sudbury, Vermont
    Sender: Darwin H. Merritt
    Letter #5
  - Recipient: Noadiah Merritt, January 27, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Sender: Parker N. Merritt
    Letter #6
  - Recipient: William B. Harris, May 5, 1846 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Address: Liverpool, Onandaga County, NY
    Sender: Cyrus Burnap
    Letter #7
    Letter seems to be a business transaction. Negative references are made to a Mr. Miller and Mr. Hoffman. Cyrus writes with concern about a money exchange, and the sale of logs.
  - Recipient: Darwin H. Merritt, July 5, 1846 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Sender: Harrison Y. Willson
    Letter #8
  - Recipient: Darwin H. Merritt, July 19, 1846 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Sender: Edwin Merritt
    Letter #9
  - Recipient: Noadiah Merritt, February 20, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Recipient: Darwin H. Merritt, March 10, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Recipient: Unknown, May 21, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Sender: Ester-Ann Merritt
  - Recipient: Noadiah Merritt, May 30, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Sender: Ellen Merritt, Parker Noadiah Merritt
  - Recipient: Darwin Merritt, August 21, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Recipient: Noadiah Merritt, September 8, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Sender: Lucy C. Merritt
  - Recipient: Unknown, June 9, 1848 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Recipient: Darwin Merritt, July 4, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Recipient: Noadiah Merritt, August 13, 1848 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Sender: C. A. Merritt
  - Recipient: Darwin Merritt, February 8, 1849 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Letter #10
  - Recipient: Unknown, March 9, 1850 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Sender: Ellen
    Letter #11
  - Recipient: Mr. Merritt, March 15, 1850 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Sender: Thomas N. Porter
    Letter #12
  - Recipient: Thomas N. Porter, March 25, 1850 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Address: Burlington, VT.
    Sender: Noadiah Merritt
    Letter #13
    Mr. Merritt addresses a grievance brought up in a previous letter from Mr. Porter. Accusations of property damage are brought up. Mr. Merritt closes by quoting several lines from the Bible: "Do unto others as ye would that they should do unto you."; "Let him that is without sin cast the first stone."; "Judge not lest ye be judged."
  - Recipient: William W. Merritt, May 1850 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Address: Albany, NY
    Sender: Anson Tolman
    Letter #14
  - Recipient: William Merritt, December 14, 1850 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Address: Russell, NY
    Letter #15
  - Recipient: W. Merritt, 1851 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Sender: E. Merritt
  - Recipient: Unknown, February 9, 1852 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Sender: Noadiah Merritt, Relief Merritt
  - Recipient: William Merritt, November 6, 1852 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Sender: Ake Y.
  - Recipient: Unknown, December 26, 1852 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Sender: P. Y. Merritt
  - Recipient: William Merritt, December 8, 1852 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Sender: Aikin Foster
  - Recipient: William Merritt, January 1, 1853 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Address: Normal School, Albany, NY
  - Recipient: William Merritt, January 1, 1853 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Recipient: William Merritt, March 23, 1853 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Sender: Leonard
    Leonard writes William about money that he, Mr. Merritt, owes to "the division." The amount totals one dollar and ninety-five cents.
  - Recipient: Unknown, January 26, 1853 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Recipient: William W. Merritt, April 10, 1853 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Sender: Sylvester Little
  - Recipient: William W. Merritt, April 10, 1853 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Sender: G. J. McIntyre
  - Recipient: William W. Merritt, April 14, 1853 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Address: Crary's Mills, St. Lawrence County, NY
  - Recipient: William W. Merritt, April 10, 1853 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Recipient: William W. Merritt, April 24, 1853 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Recipient: William W. Merritt, April 25, 1853 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Recipient: William W. Merritt, May 19, 1853 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Sender: Nell
  - Recipient: William W. Merritt, June 10, 1853 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Sender: G.Y. Merritt
  - Recipient: William W. Merritt, June 15, 1853 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Sender: Ake
  - Recipient: William W. Merritt, June 26, 1853 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Recipient: William W. Merritt, September 5, 1853 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Sender: R. Delamater
  - Recipient: Unknown, November 19, 1853 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Sender: L. F. Merritt
    Letter #16
  - Recipient: Unknown, December 25, 1853 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Letter #17
  - Recipient: Parker N. Merritt, January 17, 1854 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Address: Sudbury, NY
    Sender: Emily Merritt
  - Recipient: Darwin H. Merritt, January 12, 1853 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Recipient: Relief Merritt, October 1854 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Sender: Marshal Merritt
  - Recipient: Darwin H. Merritt, October 7, 1854 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Sender: William W. Merritt
  - Recipient: William W. Merritt, October 22, 1854 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Sender: G. Y. Merritt
  - Recipient: Unknown, NA (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Recipient: Unknown (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Recipient: Unknown (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Sender: Julius F. Merritt
  - Recipient: Unknown, November 9th (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Recipient: Unknown, October 17, 1857 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Recipient: Darwin H. Merritt, July 20, 1858 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Sender: John
  - Recipient: Darwin H. Merritt, September 28, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Recipient: Julius F. Merritt (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Sender: Emily
  - Recipient: Unknown, November 6th (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Recipient: Darwin H. Merritt (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Recipient: Unknown (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Sender: Henry. W. Merritt
    appears to be a letter written by a young child. H. H. Merritt writes on the back that it is Henry's first letter.
  - Recipient: William W. Merritt (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Sender: A. H. C.
  - Recipient: William W. Merritt (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Recipient: Julius F. Merritt, June 1853 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Sender: H. S. Merritt
  - Recipient: Unknown (Box 1, Folder 6)
    What seems to be a poem
  - Recipient: Unknown (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Recipient: Unknown (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Sender: Emily Barnard
  - Recipient: Darwin H. Merritt (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Sender: Eliza B. Merritt
  - Recipient: Unknown, March 27th (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Sender: Ellen J. Merritt
    Letter #18
  - Recipient: Darwin H. Merritt, July 17th (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Letter #19
  - Recipient: Ellen Merritt, May 14th (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Sender: Frank
    Letter #20
  - Recipient: Darwin H. Merritt, March 8, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Letter #21
  - Recipient: Unknown, May 12th (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Letter #22
  - Recipient: Unknown, November 12th (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Letter #23
  - Recipient: Unknown, January 24, 1860 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Recipient: Unknown, March 20, 1860 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Recipient: Mrs. Relief Merritt, May 10, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Recipient: Darwin H. Merritt, July 1, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Recipient: Darwin H. Merritt, March 4th (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Recipient: Unknown, July 27, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Recipient: Darwin H. Merritt, October 3rd (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Recipient: Unknown, December 25, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Recipient: Edwin Merritt, September 17th (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Recipient: Unknown, May 10, 1867 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Recipient: Unknown, January 25, 1868 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Sender: E. M. Lewis
  - Recipient: Unknown, January 9, 1869 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Recipient: Unknown (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Sender: Ed Merritt
  - Recipient: Unknown, October 17, 1869 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Recipient: Darwin H. Merritt, July 14, 1870 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Recipient: Unknown, February 28, 1880 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Sender: Jessie Fremont, Jennie Merritt
    Letter discussing the New York's prohibition laws and the states seeming support of a "Whiskey President".
  - Recipient: Darwin H. Merritt, November 6, 1879 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Sender: E. H. Landon
  - Recipient: Unknown, April 16, 1880 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Sender: W. W. Merritt
  - Recipient: Darwin H. Merritt, December 8, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    A Carte Postale sent from Paris, France. The front translates: "This side is reserved exclusively for the address"
- Newspaper Clippings and Publications
  - Speech of Honorable D. Wilmot, of Pennsylvania, in the House of Representatives discussing slavery in the territories, May 3, 1850 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Publisher: Congressional Globe Office
  - Article discussing the Northwestern Sanitary Fair (2 pages), June 15, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Publisher: Danesville Weekly Gazette
  - Entire page from a newspaper. Various printed advertisements as well as a lengthy article on the report of the New York State Fisheries Commissioners., 1884 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Publisher: Unknown
  - Envelope advertises Art Metal Light Weight Safes and a promise of burglary insurance (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Publisher: Art Metal Construction Co. Jamestown, NY
  - Postcard to be filled out and sent in to receive free burglary insurance. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Direction booklet for the Yale Combination Lock (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Publisher: The Yale & Towne Mfg. Co.
- Ledgers
  - Darwin H. Merritt Day Book: record of financial transactions, January - March 1857 (Box 2, Volume 1)
  - Record of financial transactions kept by Darwin H. Merritt, 1867-1870 (Box 2, Volume 2)
  - Darwin H. Merritt Account Book: record of financial transactions, 1859-1866 (Box 2, Volume 3)
  - Record of financial transactions kept by D. H. Merritt, Pierrepont, NY, January 1, 1881-1890 (Box 2, Volume 4)
  - Record of accounts kept by Darwin H. Merritt, 1891-1894 (Box 2, Volume 5)
  - Record of financial transactions (Very fragile: binding broken), 1818-1839 (Box 2, Volume 6)